# Lucas Swartsenburg

# Software Engineer / Product Manager / Entrepreneur

1121 euclid avenue, CA 94708, Berkeley, California US

🔰 Iswartsenburg 🔰 Iswartsenburg 🕠 Iswartsenburg 🛅 lucasswartsenburg

Experienced Software professional with a wide variety in previous roles as a Software Engineer, Solution Architect, and Technical Product Manager. Excels at data projects and products that deliver value to customers. Loves the confluence of code, product, and people.

#### **SKILLS**

#### **Software Engineering Product Management** Leadership intermediate Master Master Python Java Technical Writing Node Data Analysis Onboarding Hiring Strategy Vue / React / JS **Customer Interviews** SQL & NoSQL databases Stakeholder management Devops / Infra Product Launch CI / CD Docker / Kubernetes

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE (9)**

Software Engineer at Meta

Sep 2021 - Current

New York (US) https://www.meta.com/

- Build release infrastructure, reducing release stabalization from 5 to 2 weeks
- Internally recruited a 9 person team
- Mentored 7 young engineers

#### Engineering Team/Tech Lead at RapidAPI

Dec 2020 - Sep 2021

- San Francisco (US) https://www.rapidapi.com/
- Build engineering team from the ground up, hiring 2 engineers on the team
- Current Architect of the RapidAPI Testing product
- Guiding the product team on finding the right product strategy

#### Software Engineer at NexHealth

Jan 2020 - Dec 2020

San Francisco (US) https://www.nexhealth.com/

- Wrote integration framework supporting 30+ integrations written in Python
- Wrote 12 integrations pulling data from obscure embedded databases, a telnet server, and using web scrapers
- Deployed a 1000+ node Kubernetes cluster on AWS
- Build local caching solution, reducing load on backend with ~95%
- Hired 4 Software Engineers, 2 Support Engineers, and the VP of engineering

Co-founder at Itso / Software engineer / Product Manager

May 2019 - Jan 2020

Austin (US) https://www.itso.io/

Organized over 100 product interviews to find and validate interesting problems

- Developed "Meetics" from idea, to research and data analysis, to launch
- Interviewed with Y-Combinator

## **Product Manager** at Optimizely

#### Feb 2015 - May 2019

## San Francisco (US) https://www.optimizely.com/

- Worked with key stakeholders to launch a new way of pricing and packing, resulting in a 92% new ARR increase in the first guarter
- Re-launched the Optimizely developer website. The website is the highest rated resource available to Optimizely customers
- Launched the public REST API, adopted by 62% of paying customers, and a JS API, adopted by 86% of paying customers
- Implemented product tracking which is used to track all product OKRs
- Launched GDPR SAR automation, reducing the load on our support team with 2 FTEs
- Grew our technology partnerships from 12 to 73 within a year

## **Solution Architect** at Optimizely

Mar 2013 - Feb 2015

Amsterdam (NL) https://www.optimizely.com/

- Helped grow the EMEA headquarter from 3 to 70 employees
- Build relationships with 60 customers and developed them from presales to growth opportunity
- Created integrations with digital products which drove the creation of a "technology partner team"
- Trained new employees
- Started the development of the Optimizely certification

## Software Engineer at Zetacom

Feb 2012 - Mar 2013

▼ Zoetermeer (NL) https://www.zetacom.nl/

Developed an Android app and Python backend to access all surveillance video streams in hospitals

#### Co-founder / Software engineer at Black Stork

Feb 2012 - Mar 2013

Amsterdam (NL)

- Secured funding to develop an iOS and Android app to run Dutch auctions
- Developed and launched a Python backend, Android app, and iOS app

## Junior Web Developer at Bloomreach

Feb 2010 - Feb 2012

Amsterdam (NL)

Developed and supported a Java-based CMS for enterprise customers

### **VOLUNTEER** -

## **Startupweekend mentor** at Kauffman Foundation

Jul 2013 - Jul 2013

https://www.kauffman.org/

## **Iceskating teacher and webdeveloper** at Jeugdschaatsen Zaanstreek

Jun 2009 - Dec 2011

https://jeugdschaatsenzaanstreek.nl/

## **EDUCATION (1)**

# **Bachelor Computer Science** at University of Amsterdam

2009 - 2012

# Amsterdam, (NL)

"The bachelor's programme in Computer Science teaches students to develop and improve computer systems. In view of growing automation, it is not surprising that this new science should be on the rise. This means there

is quite a demand for well-trained computer scientists.

The programme covers computer programming, steering systems and networks, data bases and translator construction as well as artificial intelligence and multimedia. A solid theoretical foundation is provided in such fields as logic, reasoning and computability. ", UvA website

LANGUAGES ———			
English	Dutch	French	
Excellent	Native speaker	Beginner	
<b>German</b> Beginner			

#### **REFERENCES**

"I have come to appreciate Lucas as motor for change who challenges the status-quo. As a product manager and engineer, he is continuously striving to improve customer and in-house experiences by designing and building solutions. He does this through close collaboration with all relevant stakeholders (internal and external) as well by collecting data insights. Lucas is able to His product management skills paired with deep engineering expertise enables Lucas to guide teams and implement complex solutions. Lucas is a hardworking, passionate and caring team player, who is able to bring out the best in his team. I have seen him excel by forging strong relationships and joint visions. I would hire Lucas any time, if I would have an opening."

**Holger Tamm**